Hi, this is Matt Baker. Last week I did
a video exploring three different
meanings of the word Israel. Because
depending on the context, Israel could
be referring to ancient Israel or it
could be referring to the Jewish people
or it could be referring to the modern
state of Israel. Well, this week I
thought it would be suitable to follow
up with a video exploring three
different meanings of the word
Palestine. You see, when I say
Palestine, I could be referring to
Palestine as a geographic area. Or I
could be referring to the current state
of Palestine, which is recognized by 157
countries, but still under military
occupation by Israel. Or I could be
referring to some sort of more ideal
future Palestine, one in which
Palestinians either have their own state
free from occupation, i.e. a two-state
solution or one in which Arabs and Jews
live together with equal rights in some
sort of United States of Israel and
Palestine i.e. a one-state solution.
Let's start with the word Palestine as a
strictly geographic term because in this
sense the word Palestine has been in use
for a very long time and by very long I
mean at least 2,400 years. The earliest
known use of the word Palestine in the
geographic sense can be found in the
works of Heroditus the famous father of
history who lived in the 400s B.CE. In
his work histories book 3 chapter 91
when discussing the region during the
Persian period he writes in this
province was all of Phoenicia and the
part of Syria called Palestine as well
as Cyprus. Now, why would he refer to
that area as Palestine if, as we know
from Persian sources, it was also the
location at that time of a province
called Yehood, meaning Judah? Well,
here's the thing. The ancient kingdom of
Judah, which I talked about in my last
video, never really controlled the
coastal area next to it. It sometimes
made gains there, but its core territory
was always the Judeian Hill Country in
and around Jerusalem. The cities along
the coast were primarily inhabited by a
people group known as the Philistines
who show up in Egyptian, Assyrian, and
Babylonian records, as well as in the
Bible as a major enemy of the Judahites.
But around 600 B.CE, the Philistines
basically disappear from history, likely
being absorbed into Persian and then
later Greek culture, unlike the Jews who
retained a distinct identity. However,
after their disappearance, the word
Philistine, now pronounced Palestine,
continued to be used in a geographic
sense for the area where the Philistines
once lived. Now, if we move forward in
time, the coastal area becomes
controlled by the Jews for the first
time during the Hasminian and Herodian
periods and then in 6 CE ends up as a
part of the Roman province of Judea.
Now, this is important because I've
heard some people claim that Jesus was a
Palestinian, which is misleading because
he more accurately was a Jew and for his
entire adult life lived within the Roman
province of Judea. Aside from the
coastal cities, Judea was not referred
to as Palestine until about 100 years
after the death of Jesus. What happened
then was that around 135 CE, there was a
major revolt by the Jews led by a man
named Simon Barakba. In the end, the
Romans quashed the revolt and basically
raised all of Judea, killing about 2/3
of the Jewish population there and
deporting most of the rest. In order to
further punish the Jews, the Romans
renamed the entire province Palestine
after the Jews old enemy, the
Philistines. And ever since then,
Palestine has been the primary
geographic name for the area. For
example, when the area was conquered by
the Arabs and then later by the Turks,
they continued to use the name,
pronouncing it Philistine. Even the Jews
who continued to live in the area and
then the early Zionists originally
referred to themselves as Palestinian
Jews in contrast to the Palestinian
Arabs. It was only after the creation of
the state of Israel in 1948 that the
Jews living there became known as
Israelis with the word Palestinian
generally being reserved for the Arab
residents only including both Muslims
and Christians. But even so, the word
Palestine can still be used to describe
the overall geographic area now
controlled by Israel and is in fact
sometimes still used in that way,
especially in academic contexts.
However, these days the term Southern
Leavant is increasingly used in order to
avoid any confusion. Now, before I
continue, I want to shout out today's
sponsor, Ground News, which is the
website and app that I use to keep up
with events happening around the world.
What makes Ground News different is that
it pulls headlines from multiple
sources, including newspapers, podcasts,
and websites. It then categorizes them
on a continuum from left to right so
that you get to look at the same news
story from multiple angles. Something
that is particularly important when it
comes to events happening in say the
Middle East. For example, here's a story
about a recent survey that asked
American Jews what they thought about
the Israel Gaza situation. Notice how
this left-wing source reported a decline
in support for Israel, whereas this
right-wing source reported that opinions
were divided. Ground News also has a
blind spot feed, which highlights
stories that one side of the spectrum is
barely covering at all. For example,
very few right-wing sources covered this
story about how US support for Israel is
slipping, whereas very few left-wing
sources covered this story about how the
Democrats are divided on the issue. As
you can see, by checking the blindspot
feed, you can avoid getting trapped in
your usual media bubble. So, don't wait.
Subscribe now by going to
ground.news/charts
or by using the link in the description
or pinned comment. If you use that
address or link, you will get 40% off
unlimited access to their Vantage plan.
Again, that's ground.news/charts.
Okay, returning to the different
meanings of the word Palestine. As we've
already seen, the word Palestine in the
geographic sense has been in use for a
very long time. But you see, ever since
the Philistines disappeared and the
ancient Jews were mostly kicked out, the
inhabitants of Palestine have never been
independent. Instead, it's just been a
steady stream of one foreign invader
after another. So when it comes to their
DNA, the modern Palestinians are likely
a mix of Canaanite, Egyptian,
Philistine, Israelite, Persian, Greek,
Roman, Northern Arab, Southern Arab,
European crusader, even more Arab, and
Turk. In other words, they likely
descend at least a little bit from every
people group that has ever lived or
passed through the area. But the
important thing to note is that they do
not primarily just descend from the
Arabs who took over Palestine during the
Muslim conquests of the 7th century.
Recent studies have shown that despite
all the foreign invaders, a good portion
of their DNA also matches very closely
to the Bronze Age Canaanites who lived
there 4,000 years ago. Now, some people
argue that since the Palestinians have
never had their own state in the past,
that they don't deserve to have one
today. Well, that's ridiculous because
most countries formed during the 20th
and 21st centuries were created not
based on past independence, but based on
the recognition that the people living
there in the present share a common
language, culture, history, and
religion. In fact, had it not been for
the Zionist movement, Palestine almost
certainly would have achieved
independence around the same time and in
the same manner that other nearby
countries did. You see, in the years
following World War I, Britain and
France recognized that the Levant should
be divided into four new countries.
Palestine, Jordan, Lebanon, and Syria.
In fact, they provisionally recognized
the independence of all four countries
while at the same time governing them as
separate mandatories. But keep in mind
that the goal of these mandatories was
simply to provide temporary assistance.
In the case of Jordan, Lebanon, and
Syria, all three achieved full
independence by 1946, but Palestine did
not. This is because the British
promised the land to both the local Arab
inhabitants as well as to the Zionist
settlers. In 1947, the UN attempted to
fix the problem by proposing the
creation of two Palestinian states, one
for Arabs and one for Jews. However,
because the Zionists agreed but the
Arabs did not, a war ensued, resulting
in the creation of the state of Israel
as well as the Nagba, in which an
estimated 750,000 Palestinian Arabs were
displaced. The majority ended up in
either the Gaza Strip, which became a
military protectorate of Egypt, or the
West Bank, which was annexed by Jordan.
But then came the 6- day war in 1967 in
which Israel captured these two areas.
And ever since then, Israel has had in
one way or another control over both the
Gaza Strip and the West Bank, which are
now often referred to as the Palestinian
territories. So, how then did the
current state of Palestine come to
exist? Well, as you can imagine, it's a
bit complicated. During the 1960s a
coalition known as the PLO or Palestine
Liberation Organization was founded and
during the 1970s they now led by Yaser
Arafat were recognized by most of the
world as the main representative of the
Palestinian people. Initially they
advocated for the complete dismantling
of the state of Israel and occasionally
used violence to work towards that goal.
In 1988, they even declared
independence, proclaiming that
everything within the borders of what
had been mandatory Palestine was now the
state of Palestine. Of course, this was
only on paper because in reality, Israel
still controlled all of that area. But
then in 1993, a major change occurred.
In what is known as the Oslo Accord, the
PLO renounced violence and recognized
Israel's right to exist. in return for
Israel recognizing the PLO as the sole
representative of the Palestinian people
and agreeing to let them have some
self-governance within the West Bank and
Gaza. Since then, the number of UN
member states recognizing the state of
Palestine has increased to 157, which is
about 81%. But still, the state of
Palestine does not have full
independence. Even when Israel withdrew
their military from Gaza in 2005, it
still maintained full control over its
airspace, seapports, border crossings,
population registry, electricity grid,
and so on. Of course, as of 2026, 90% of
Gaza now lies in ruins. In the West
Bank, Israel continues to have an even
tighter grip, not to mention the many
illegal settlements it has there. So
that's the current situation in
Palestine as defined by the second
definition, meaning the official state
of Palestine. On paper, it exists. But
in reality, the people there have very
little actual freedom. Which brings me
to the third definition of Palestine,
the one that is evoked every time
someone shouts free Palestine or holds
up a sign with those words. Every time
that happens, a new Palestine is being
envisioned. either one in which the
Palestinian people have full sovereignty
over both the Gaza Strip and the West
Bank or one in which the Palestinian
people enjoy the same rights and
freedoms as the Israelis currently do.
Obviously, when and how this future
Palestine will come to fruition is
totally up in the air right now. Lots of
solutions to the current conflict have
been proposed over the years, but so far
none have been accepted by the two sides
involved. So to sum up, here's a chart
explaining the three meanings of the
word Palestine. The first meaning covers
Palestine as a geographic term, which
from 600 B.CE to 135 CE referred only to
the former Philistine territories, but
from 135 C onwards refers to everything
from the Jordan River to the
Mediterranean Sea. The second meaning
refers to the state of Palestine
established in 1988. A state which
currently exists on paper but not in
reality because it has never had full
sovereignty. Finally, the third meaning
refers to a future Palestine. One in
which everyone living in the geographic
region of Palestine will have full
rights and freedoms. So that was a look
at the word Palestine. If you want to
keep up with the latest news from that
region of the world, be sure to sign up
for Ground News using the link in the
description or pinned comment or by
going to groundnews.com/charts.
Thanks for [music] watching.